A Guide to the Henry Rose Carter Papers 1775-1947
Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
Henry Rose Carter Papers, 1775-1947
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-10
5.25 linear feet
Administrative Information
Access
No Restrictions
Biographical/Historical Information
Henry Rose Carter was born on Clifton Plantation, Caroline County, Virginia, August 25, 1851 or 1852. He attended Aspen Hill Academy in Louisa County, Virginia, and completed studies there in 1868. After teaching in a boys school in Nelson County, Virginia, he entered the University of Virginia, where he earned proficiency certificates in Mineralogy and Geology, and in Physics, and a diploma from the School of Pure Mathematics in June of 1872. In July 1873, he earned diplomas from the Schools of General and Industrial Chemistry, Natural Philosophy, Applied Mathematics, and Civil Engineering. Subsequently Carter pursued an interest in Medicine, and he recieved an M.D. degree from the University of Maryland in March of 1879. That year he joined the Marine Hospital Service (later the United States Public Health Service) and over his career ascended through the ranks to become Assistant Surgeon General in 1915.
Initial postings with the Service took him to Cairo, Illinois -- where he met and married Laura Hook, of St. Louis, Missouri, on September 29, 1880 -- Memphis, Tennessee; San Francisco, California; and New Orleans, Louisiana. The Service detailed him as a quarantine officer to Ship Island, Mississippi in 1888, and here began his researches with yellow fever, which he would quickly refine to an extremely high level of expertise. Carter's thorough and methodical observations of the appearance and development of the disease proved critical to Dr. Walter Reed's landmark demonstration of the mosquito transmission of yellow fever in 1900. Assigned to Cuba in 1899, Carter's tour of duty overlapped with those of Reed and the other members of the famous United States Army Yellow Fever Commission, who were able to learn first-hand of Carter's most recent conclusions.
Carter's long and distinguished sanitary career took him to the Panama Canal Zone in 1904, where he served as Chief Quarantine Officer and Chief of Hospitals for five years. He also undertook detailed investigations and control measures of malaria in North Carolina and elsewhere in the South, and became a founder of the National Malaria Committee. With the support of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Board, he undertook additional investigation and control measures for yellow fever in Central and South America. His expertise recommended him to the Peruvian government, which named Carter Sanitary Advisor in 1920-1921.
Health problems at the end of his life compelled Carter to withdraw from active fieldwork, though he remained a highly valued consultant to the Health Board and a much-beloved and respected teacher for a new generation of sanitarians. Carter closed his career researching and writing the manuscript that his daughter, Laura Armistead Carter, edited and published posthumously in 1931: Yellow Fever: An Epidemiological and Historical Study of its Place of Origin.
Scope and Content Information
The Carter Papers include correspondence relating to Carter's work on yellow fever and malaria as a surgeon in the Marine Health Service (later United States Public Health Service) and notes for drafts of his Yellow Fever: An Epidemiological and Historical Study of its Place of Origin.(Baltimore: The Williams and Wilkins Company, 1931). Included are photographs of and newspaper clippings about Carter, in addition to a small collection of reprints and publications by Carter and others. Also included is the correspondence of his daughter, Laura Armistead Carter with Frederick F. Russell and other members of the Rockefeller Foundation International Health Board, Wade Hampton Frost, of Johns Hopkins University, and others concerning her collaboration with Frost in the editing and publication of Carter's book. Also included are a series of eighteenth-century to mid-nineteenth-century documents principally belonging to Carter's great-grandfather, George Mason, of Spotsylvania and Caroline Counties, Virginia and to Mary Ann Brown, sister of Carter's mother.
Special Note: This collection should be consulted in conjunction with the Philip S. Hench Walter Reed Yellow Fever Collection, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, Department of Historical Collections and Services, MS 1 (and in online version: http://yellowfever.lib.virginia.edu), containing a substantial complementary deposit of Henry Rose Carter papers.
Organization
The collection has been organized into four groups. The bulk of the documents are arranged in chronological order, following these are folders of photographs. Reprints have been arranged by author's last name, and a final grouping contains oversize items -- diplomas, etc., -- and artifacts.
Contents List
- PLAT, LAND IN SPOTSYLVANIA COUNTY, VIRGINIA BY WILLIAM PETTIT FOR MR. CRAWFORD 1775, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-001)
  THIS AND SUBSEQUENT 18TH AND EARLY 19TH CENTURY PAPERS BELONGED TO GEORGE MASON OF CAROLINE COUNTY, VIRGINIA, GREAT GRANDFATHER OF HENRY ROSE CARTER.
- INDENTURE: JAMES AND SUSANNAH KING TO WILLIAM HUELL, SPOTSYLVANIA COUNTY, VIRGINIA 1781/08/16, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-002)
  THIS DOCUMENT BELONGED TO GEORGE MASON OF CAROLINE COUNTY, VIRGINIA, GREAT GRANDFATHER OF HENRY ROSE CARTER.
- ACCOUNT: JOHN WALLER TO THOMAS POWELL, RECORDED BY GEORGE MASON 1786/02/24, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-003)
- BOND: WILLIAM HEWELL TO GEORGE MASON, SPOTSYLVANIA COUNTY, VIRGINIA 1787/02/17, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-004)
- BOND: HENRY TERREL AND THOMAS MINOR TO SHARP SMITH, SPOTSYLVANIA COUNTY, VIRGINIA. WITNESSED BY GEORGE MASON 1787/10/02, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-005)
- COURT ORDER: APPOINTING PETER MASON GUARDIAN TO ASA AND MARY CHAPMAN, FAYETTE COUNTY [KENTUCKY?] 1791/01, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-006)
- RECEIPT: DUDLEY MITCHUM TO GEORGE MASON 1791/05, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-007)
- RECEIPT: CHARLES MASON FOR EDMUND SINGLETON TO [UNKNOWN] 1795/09, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-008)
- ACCOUNT: EDMUND SINGLETON WITH GEORGE MASON 1795/09/02, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-009)
- ACCOUNT: EDMUND SINGLETON TO GEORGE MASON 1796, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-010)
- BOND: FANNY MASON, WILLIAM DILLARD, AND WILLIAM WHITE TO GEORGE MASON, EXECUTOR OR JAMES MASON 1815/11/28, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-012)
- RECORD OF THE DIVISION OF JAMES MASON'S ESTATE, BETWEEN FANNY MASON, WILLIAM DILLARD, AND WILLIAM WHITE. PREPARED BY GEORGE MASON 1815/11/28, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-013)
- LETTER FROM SALLY [COLEMAN] TO [HER MOTHER] MRS. N. W. COLEMAN 1835/06/22, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-014)
- ACCOUNT: GEORGE MASON WITH JOHNSON NEWTON [FOR BLACKSMITHING] 1839/01/10, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-015)
- BILL OF SALE: MARY ANN BROWN TO HENRY R. CARTER [SR.] [FOR THREE SLAVES] 1853/01/25, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-016)
- WILL: MARY ANN BROWN, HANOVER COUNTY, VIRGINIA 1856/03/27, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-017)
  SISTER OF HENRY ROSE CARTER'S MOTHER
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NATURAL PHILOSOPHY NOTEBOOK, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA [1872-1873], 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-018)
- LAURA HOOK, CORRESPONDENCE AND TEACHING CERTIFICATES RELATED TO HER CAREER AS A TEACHER IN ILLINOIS 1872-1879, 7 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-019)
- LAURA HOOK, RECORDS OF FAMILY BURIAL ARRANGEMENTS 1879/07, 3 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-020)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE STATE OF LOUISANA BOARD OF HEALTH, DRS. G. FARRAR PATTON AND EDMOND SOUCHON 1898/08/09; 1898/0909, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-021)
- YELLOW FEVER CHARTS, TAKEN FROM J. C. FAGET 1898, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-022)
  SEE REPRINTS, BOX 6, FOLDER 4
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MANUSCRIPT AND REPRINT (PHOTOSTATS) OF HIS ARTICLE ON EXTRINSIC INCUBATION OF YELLOW FEVER 1898-1901, 5 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-023)
  "A NOTE ON THE INTERVAL BETWEEN INFECTING AND SECONDARY CASES OF YELLOW FEVER FROM THE RECORDS OF THE YELLOW FEVER AT ORWOOD AND TAYLOR, MISS., 1898" NEW ORLEANS MEDICAL AND SURGICAL JOURNAL 50 (MAY, 1900)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1899-1905, 4 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-024)
- UNIVERSITY OF PENNSYLVANIA, ANNOUNCEMENT OF GRADUATION 1908, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-025)
  HENRY ROSE CARTER ON "JUBILATION COMMITTEE"
- [HENRY ROSE CARTER ?] LIST OF BONDS AND NOTES ON FEVER CASES 1910-1915, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-026)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH LAURA A. CARTER AND EDWARD CARTER 1911 (Box-folder 01-027)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1911-1918, 12 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-028)
- DOUGLAS S. FREEMAN, EXERPT FROM RICHMOND NEWS LEADER EDITORIAL "CARTER, REED, GORGAS." 1914/11/10, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-029)
- ALBANY (N.Y.) PRESS-KNICK, "MALARIA"; WASHINGTON TIMES, "SURGEONS PROMOTED FOR CANAL SERVICE." 1915/01/16; 1915/03/12, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-030)
- MANUSCRIPT (IN SPANISH) OF PAPER READ BEFORE THE PAN-AMERICAN SCIENTIFIC CONGRESS (SECTION ON PUBLIC HEALTH), WASHINGTON, D.C., DECEMBER 1915 1915/12, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 01-031)
  PUBLISHED IN THE ANNALS OF TROPICAL MEDICINE AND PARISITOLOGY (LIVERPOOL, ENGLAND) APRIL 1916
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MEMORANDUM ON MALARIA [1918-1925, CA.], 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-032)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1921, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-033)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1922, 20 ITEMS (Box-folder 01-034)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NOTES AND MANUSCRIPT FOR HIS HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER 1922-1925 (Box-folder 02-001)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NOTES AND MANUSCRIPT FOR HIS HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER 1922-1925 (Box-folder 02-002)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NOTES AND MANUSCRIPT FOR HIS HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER 1922-1925 (Box-folder 02-003)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NOTES AND MANUSCRIPT FOR HIS HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER 1922-1925 (Box-folder 02-004)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NOTES AND MANUSCRIPT FOR HIS HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER 1922-1925 (Box-folder 02-005)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NOTES AND MANUSCRIPT FOR HIS HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER 1922-1925 (Box-folder 02-006)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, NOTES AND MANUSCRIPT FOR HIS HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER 1922-1925 (Box-folder 02-007)
- EL TELEGRAFO "EL ESTADO SANITARIO" 1923/02/10, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 03-001)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1923, 42 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-002)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1923, 4 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-003)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE AUTHORS' CLUB 1923-1926, 9 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-004)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER TO DR. FRICKS; HENRY ROSE CARTER TO MARY [C. CARTER] [HIS SISTER] 1924/04/27; N.D., 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-005)
- TRANSCRIPT OF A CONVERSATION BETWEEN DRS. CARTER, THAYER, AND PARKER, RE: YELLOW FEVER WORK, REED, FINLAY, CARROLL, AND LAZEAR TAKEN BY LAURA A. CARTER 1924, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 03-006)
  CONTAINS IMPORTANT INFORMATION ON CARTER'S INVOLVEMENT WITH JESSE LAZEAR AND WALTER REED IN CUBA, 1900
- BOLIVAR J. LLOYD, OBITUARY OF HENRY ROSE CARTER [1925/09/14], 1 ITEM (Box-folder 03-007)
- THE BOSTON GLOBE [OBITUARY FOR HENRY ROSE CARTER BY MAYME OBER PEAK], "HIS RACE WITH DEATH WON BY LAST OF THE YELLOW FEVER PIONEERS." 1925/11/24, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-008)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1925, 5 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-009)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH FREDERICK F. RUSSELL AND THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION 1925, 6 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-010)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH WADE H. FROST 1926/09/09, 3 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-011)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1925, 17 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-012)
- LAURA A. CARTER TO [?] 1926[01/10], 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-013)
  CONCERNING HENRY ROSE CARTER'S LIFE AND WORK
- ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD, MINUTES CONCERNING HENRY ROSE CARTER 1926/11/04, 3 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-014)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH FREDERICK F. RUSSELL AND THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION 1926, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-015)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH WADE H. FROST 1927/07/13, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 03-016)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1926, 8 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-017)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH FREDERICK F. RUSSELL AND THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION 1927, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-018)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1927, 5 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-019)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MEMORANDUM OF A CONVERSATION WITH DR. SYLVANUS 1928/12, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-020)
  CONCERNING MAPS FOR HENRY ROSE CARTER'S HISTORY OF YELLOW FEVER
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH WADE H. FROST 1928, 16 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-021)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH FREDERICK F. RUSSELL AND THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION 1928, 53 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-022)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1928, 29 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-023)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH THE LIBRARY OF CONGRESS 1928-1930, N.D., 11 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-024)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH WADE H. FROST 1929, 7 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-025)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH FREDERICK F. RUSSELL AND THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION 1929, 37 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-026)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1929, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-027)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH WADE H. FROST 1930, 1930 CA., 40 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-028)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH FREDERICK F. RUSSELL AND THE ROCKEFELLER FOUNDATION 1930, 5 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-029)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1930, 6 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-030)
- "DAUGHTER CARRIES ON FATHER'S WORK" [1931 CA.]/11/29, 3 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-031)
  NEWSPAPER GALLEY PROOFS
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1931, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 03-032)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1932, 3 ITEMS (Box-folder 03-033)
- NOTEBOOK OF WORTHWHILE SAYINGS, UNKNOWN AUTHOR 1934, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 04-001)
  FOUND AMIDST HENRY ROSE CARTER'S NOTES FOR HIS YELLOW FEVER HISTORY
- LIST OF ARTICLES ON YELLOW FEVER AND MALARIA BY DR. H. R. CARTER 1935/08/31 CA., 1 ITEM (Box-folder 04-002)
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS CORRESPONDENCE 1935, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-003)
- LAURA A. CARTER, CORRESPONDENCE WITH "MAYME" AND EDWARD C. CARTER 1935, N.D., 3 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-004)
- SUMMARY AND NOTES ON HENRY ROSE CARTER'S LIFE AND WORK 1937-1938 CA., 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-005)
- T. H. D. GRIFFITTS TO MARY C. CARTER 1938/11/02, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-006)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, JR. TO MARY CARTER 1947/01/01, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-007)
  CONCERNING PHILIP S. HENCH'S RESEARCH ON YELLOW FEVER
- MARY C. CARTER TO DR. JAMES LEAKE 1947/01/22, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-008)
  CONCERNING HER BROTHER HENRY ROSE CARTER'S YELLOW FEVER WORK, ETC.
- PHILIP S. HENCH TO H. CARTER REDD, AND H. CARTER REDD TO PHILIP S. HENCH 1947/12/09; 1947/12/19, 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-009)
- MANUSCRIPT: HENRY ROSE CARTER, "ANTI-MALARIAL MEASURES FOR FARM HOUSES AND PLANTATIONS." N.D., 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-010)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER TO MR. BRUCE N.D. [1920 CA.], 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-011)
  CONCERNS THE CONNECTION BETWEEN CARTER'S WORK IN MISSISSIPPI AND WALTER REED'S WORK IN CUBA. NOTE IDENTIFYING BRUCE AS WILLIAM CABELL BRUCE IS PROBABLY MISTAKEN -- IS POSSIBLY PHILIP ALEXANDER BRUCE, AUTHOR OF THE HISTORY OF UVA, 1921
- LAURA A. CARTER, MISCELLANEOUS NOTES OR CORRESPONDENCE N.D., 6 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-012)
- NOTES AND TYPED MANUSCRIPT, "EARLY LIFE OF DR. H. R. CARTER" N.D., 2 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-013)
- RESEARCH NOTES ON CARTER PAPERS N.D., 1 ITEM (Box-folder 04-014)
- TIMELINE AND NOTES ON HENRY ROSE CARTER'S EARLY LIFE AND WORK. FRAGMENTARY ACCOUNT OF CARTER'S YELLOW FEVER WORK [IN SPANISH] N.D. (Box-folder 04-015)
- VIRGINIA DOUGLAS STRACHAN TO HELEN N.D., 1 ITEM (Box-folder 04-016)
- PHOTOGRAPH, FRAMED PORTRAIT OF W. C. GORGAS 1909/07/24, PHOTOGRAPH, 1 ITEM (Box-folder 04-017)
  INSCRIBED TO LAURA [A. CARTER]
- PHOTOGRAPHS, HENRY ROSE CARTER 1909, N.D., PHOTOGRAPHS, 13 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-018)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, LAURA A. CARTER 1924, 1933, N.D., PHOTOGRAPHS, 6 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-019)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, MISCELLANEOUS 1930, N.D., PHOTOGRAPHS, 23 ITEMS (Box-folder 04-020)
- "HENRY ROSE CARTER" 1925, 2 REPRINTS (Box-folder 05-001)
  AMERICAN JOURNAL OF TROPICAL MEDICINE 5:6
- "HENRY ROSE CARTER" 1925/10, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 05-002)
  THE BULLETIN OF THE INTERNATIONAL HEALTH BOARD 6:2
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "NOTES ON THE SANITATION OF YELLOW FEVER AND MALARIA, FROM ISTHMIAN EXPERIENCE" 1908, REPRINT (Box-folder 05-003)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "ANTIMALARIAL MEASURES FOR FARMHOUSES AND PLANTATIONS" 1912, REPRINT (Box-folder 05-004)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "THE EFFECT OF IMPOUNDED WATER ON THE INCIDENCE OF MALARIA" 1914, REPRINT (Box-folder 05-005)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "MALARIA: LESSONS ON ITS CAUSE AND PREVENTION" 1914, 3 REPRINTS (Box-folder 05-006)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "THE MALARIA PROBLEM OF THE SOUTH" 1917/01/25-26, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 05-007)
  PROCEEDINGS OF THE FOURTH ANNUAL MEETING OF THE NEW JERSEY MOSQUITO EXTERMINATION ASSOCIATION
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "THE MECHANISM OF THE SPONTANEOUS ELIMINATION OF YELLOW FEVER FROM ENDEMIC CENTERS" 1919, 5 REPRINTS (Box-folder 05-008)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "RESUME OF METHODS FOR CONTROL OF MALARIA: INDICATIONS; RESULTS; COSTS" 1919, 2 REPRINTS (Box-folder 05-009)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, DISCUSSANT, "TROPICAL DISEASES AND PUBLIC HEALTH" 1920/04, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 05-010)
  SOUTHERN MEDICAL JOURNAL 13:4
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "YELLOW FEVER IN PERU: EPIDEMIC OF 1919 AND 1920" 1921, 4 REPRINTS (Box-folder 05-011)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, DISCUSSANT, "TROPICAL DISEASES AND PUBLIC HEALTH" 1922/05, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 05-012)
  SOUTHERN MEDICAL JOURNAL 15:5
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "'MAN MADE' MALARIA" 1922, 14 REPRINTS (Box-folder 05-013)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "THE CHANCE OF THE EXTENSION OF YELLOW FEVER TO ASIA AND AUSTRALASIA" N.D. [AFTER 1923], 2 REPRINTS (Box-folder 05-014)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, "THE EFFECT OF VARIATION OF LEVEL OF IMPOUNDED WATER ON THE CONTROL OF ANOPHELES PRODUCTION" 1924/08, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 05-015)
  SOUTHERN MEDICAL JOURNAL 17:8
- O. F. COOK, "FOOD PLANTS OF ANCIENT AMERICA" 1903, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-001)
- W. E. DEEKS, "MALARIA: ITS CAUSE, PREVENTION AND CURE" 1925, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 06-002)
  (BOSTON, MASS.: UNITED FRUIT COMPANY)
- H. Z. DON, "DIE KAISERLICHE FAMILIE IN LEQUEITIO" [IN GERMAN] 1924, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-003)
- J. C. FAGET, "THE TYPE AND SPECIFICITY OF YELLOW FEVER" 1875, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 06-004)
  (PARIS: J. B. BALLIERE & SONS; NEW ORLEANS: AM. LUTTON) SEE BOX 1 FOLDER 22 FOR FEVER CHARTS FROM THIS WORK
- JUAN RODRIGUEZ FRESLE, "CONQUISTA Y DESCUBRIMIENTO DEL NUEVO REINO DE GRANADA" [IN SPANISH] 1890, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 06-005)
  (BOGOTA: SAMPER MATIZ)
- W. C. GORGAS, H. R. CARTER, T. C. LYSTER, "YELLOW FEVER: ITS DISTRIBUTION AND CONTROL IN 1920" 1920, 14 REPRINTS (Box-folder 06-006)
- T. H. D. GRIFFITTS, "HEALTH AND HYDRO-ELECTRIC STORAGE DEVELOPMENTS" 1926/05, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 06-007)
  AQUAFAX 2:12
- L. O. HOWARD, "CONCERNING THE GEOGRAPHIC DISTRIBUTION OF THE YELLOW FEVER MOSQUITO" 1903, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-008)
- LORD KELVIN, "ON ETHER AND GRAVITATIONAL MATTER THROUGH INFINITE SPACE" 1901, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-009)
- C. J. KEMPER, "CENTRAL FORCES" 1878, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-010)
- W. S. LEATHERS, "THE ROLE OF THE UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA IN PUBLIC HEALTH WORK" 1923/07, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 06-011)
  ALUMNI BULLETIN, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA
- LIBRARY OF CONGRESS, "REPORT OF THE LIBRARIAN OF CONGRESS" 1929, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 06-012)
  (WASHINGTON: UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT PRINTING OFFICE)
- HIDEYO NOGUCHI, "ETIOLOGY OF YELLOW FEVER: MOSQUITOES IN RELATION TO YELLOW FEVER" 1919, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-013)
- ROBERT P. PARSONS, "HISTORY OF HAITIAN MEDICINE" 1929, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-014)
- THEODORE ROOSEVELT, "PANAMA CANAL" 1903, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-015)
  SENATE DOCUMENT NO. 32, 58TH CONGRESS, 2ND SESSION
- ROYAL SOCIETY OF TROPICAL MEDICINE AND HYGIENE, "YEARBOOK OF THE SOCIETY" 1922-1923, PUBLICATION (Box-folder 06-016)
  (LONDON: ROYAL SOCIETY OF TROPICAL MEDICINE AND HYGIENE)
- "SOME ACHIEVEMENTS OF AN EMINENT AMERICAN SANITARIAN" 1915, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-017)
  SOUTHERN MEDICAL JOURNAL 8:6
- E. R. STITT, "THE MEDICAL DEPARTMENT IN BATTLE AT SEA" 1925, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-018)
- EDWARD R. STITT, "RESULTS OF IMPROVED MEDICAL EDUCATION IN THE GOVERNMENT MEDICAL SERVICES" 1925, 4 REPRINTS (Box-folder 06-019)
- E. R. STITT, "UNDERGRADUATE DEFICIENCIES AND POST GRADUATE REQUIREMENTS" 1925, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-020)
- E. R. STITT, "OUR DISEASE INHERITANCE FROM SLAVERY" 1928, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-021)
- J. J. THOMSON, "ON BODIES SMALLER THAN ATOMS" 1902, REPRINT (Box-folder 06-022)
- "THE UNITED STATES PUBLIC HEALTH SERVICE" 1938, 3 PUBLICATIONS (Box-folder 06-023)
  VIRGINIA DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH, HEALTH BULLETIN 2:11
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CERTIFICATE OF PROFICIENCY, CLASS OF MINERALOGY AND GEOLOGY, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA 1872/06/27, CERTIFICATE (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CERTIFICATE OF PROFICIENCY, CLASS OF PHYSICS, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA 1872/06/27, CERTIFICATE (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, GRADUATE IN THE SCHOOL OF PURE MATHEMATICS, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA 1872/06/27, DIPLOMA (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, GRADUATE IN THE SCHOOL OF GENERAL AND INDUSTRIAL CHEMISTRY, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA 1873/07/03, DIPLOMA (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, GRADUATE IN THE SCHOOL OF NATURAL PHILOSOPHY, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA 1873/07/03, DIPLOMA (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, GRADUATE IN THE SCHOOL OF APPLIED MATHEMATICS, UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA 1873/07/03, DIPLOMA (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, GRADUATE IN THE SCHOOL OF CIVIL ENGINEERING, WITH TITLE OF "CIVIL ENGINEER," UNIVERSITY OF VIRGINIA 1873/07/03, DIPLOMA (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, DEGREE OF MEDICAL DOCTOR, UNIVERSITY OF MARYLAND 1879/03/01, DIPLOMA (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CERTIFICATION OF RIGHT TO PRACTICE MEDICINE, STATE BOARD OF HEALTH, STATE OF ILLINOIS 1879/11/28, LICENSE (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, APPOINTMENT AS "PASSED ASSISTANT SURGEON," IN THE MARINE HEALTH SERVICE OF THE UNITED STATES 1889/10/21, CERTIFICATE (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CERTIFICATE OF ELECTION TO THE AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION 1890/12/16-19, CERTIFICATE (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, SCRAPBOOK, "A BOOK OF GOLDEN DEEDS" 1897-1910, SCRAPBOOK (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CERTIFICATE OF ELECTION TO THE AMERICAN PUBLIC HEALTH ASSOCIATION 1902/12/08-12, CERTIFICATE (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, UNITED STATES PASSPORT 1916/06/12, PASSPORT (Box-folder 07-)
- HENRY ROSE CARTER, CERTIFICATE OF ELECTION AS A FELLOW OF THE AMERICAN ASSOCIATION FOR THE ADVANCEMENT OF SCIENCE 1917/12/31, CERTIFICATE (Box-folder 07-)
- ENVELOPE CONTAINING EYEGLASS FRAME PIECES, 2 STUDS, AND 2 PINS N.D., ARTIFACT (Box-folder 07-)
  BELONGING TO HENRY ROSE CARTER AND LAURA A. CARTER
- JEWEL BOX CONTAINING MILITARY INSIGNIA: EAGLE, AND "U.S." N.D., ARTIFACT (Box-folder 07-)
  BELONGING TO HENRY ROSE CARTER
- LETTER OPENER, SILVER HANDLE INSCRIBED "C" N.D., ARTIFACT (Box-folder 07-)
- TIN BOX CONTAINING BUTTONS, WIRE, PEN NIBS, AND OTHER MISCELLANEOUS ITEMS N.D., ARTIFACT (Box-folder 07-)